Guide to the Lionel Barrow Papers, 1940-2008 RL.00084
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lionel Barrow papers
1940-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Barrow, Lionel C., 1926-2009
RL.00084
48.3 Linear Feet
Dean of Howard University School of Communications, 1975-1985; founder of the Minorities and Communications Division of the Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication. Collection includes materials from Lionel Barrow's advertising career, his teaching and tenure at Howard University, and his involvement in the Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC). The earliest materials include student work from Barrow's youth and his studies at Morehouse College, as well as materials from his service in the 24th Infantry Regiment during the Korean War. Another significant portion of the collection is Barrow's newspaper clippings and subject files, dating largely from the 1960s-2000s. His research on an unfinished book about the Freedom's Journal is also a large component of the collection. Also included are numerous photographs, some dating as early as the 1950s, but the bulk of which date 1982-2000s. These include family vacations and events, as well as professional events with AEJMC, the National Association of Black Journalists, and other conferences and organizations. Another notable component of the collection is the section of materials from Barrow's mother, Wilhelmina Barrow, who served as an American Red Cross Girl in Europe during World War II and the post-war period. Acquired as part of the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Lionel Barrow Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2010 and 2017.
Biographical Note
Lionel C. Barrow, Jr., was born in New York in 1926 to Lionel C. and Wilhelmina Barrow. He attended Morehouse College and graduated with Martin Luther King in 1948. He also served in the U.S. Army from 1945 to 1947, and from 1950 to 1953.
Barrow attended the School of Journalism at the University of Wisconsin, earning his master's degree in 1958 and a doctorate in mass communication in 1960. Subsequently, he worked in advertising as a researcher, and in 1968 became vice president and associate director of research at the Foote, Cone and Belding agency in New York. Barrow became the dean of Howard University's School of Communications in 1975, where he worked until 1985. He married his wife, Frederica, in 1992; the couple eventually settled in Florida.
Along with his academic interests, Barrow was an active member of the Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication, and was a principle force in helping the organization begin to promote diversity in the field. He founded the Ad Hoc Committee on Minority Education in 1968, and expanded to also form the Minorities and Communication Division in 1970. An AEJMC scholarship was created in his honor to assist women and minorities in their graduate journalism education.
Barrow was also active in politics, fundraising and campaigning for Democratic candidates as early as the 1960s and as recently as the Barack Obama presidential campaign in 2008. He died shortly after Obama's inauguration in January 2009.
Collection Overview
The collection includes materials from Barrow's advertising career, his teaching and tenure at Howard University, and his involvement in the Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC). AEJMC materials include a series of folders from a diversity survey in 2004; files from the founding and the operations of the Minorities and Communications Division; and programs and reports from AEJMC activities, especially in the 1970s and 1980s. Materials also reflect Barrow's involvement in the Council for Opportunities in Education, in particular his promotion of the TRIO program, offering funding and education opportunities for underprivileged youth.
A small part of the collection is Barrow's educational materials, dated 1940s-1970s, including reports and essays from his years at Morehouse College as well as his Ph.D. proposals and notes from the University of Wisconsin.
Also included are materials from his service in the 24th Infantry Regiment during the Korean War. The Korean War material, dated 1950-1951, includes press releases, written by Barrow, regarding various battles and army movements. Also included is correspondence to his mother, Wilhelmina Barrow, discussing his activities, as well as his struggles with payment and segregation in the U.S. Army.
Another significant portion of the collection is Barrow's newspaper clippings, dating largely from the 1960s-2000s, covering racial integration and the Civil Rights movement in Washington D.C., issues in journalism, and diversity and the condition of black Americans. These clippings have been loosely arranged by Barrow according to the date, the person's name, or the subject.
There are also numerous folders with clippings and research from Barrow's unfinished book on the history of the Freedom's Journal, the first African-American owned and operated newspaper in the United States. Subjects include slavery, education, conditions in different states, and other information about American life in the 1820s.
Also included are numerous photographs, some dating as early as the 1950s, but the bulk of which date from 1982 to the 2000s. The majority of the photographs are snapshots, many featuring the Barrow family and its activities. There are also snapshots of professional events with AEJMC, the National Association of Black Journalists, and other conferences and organizations. The photographs have not been arranged, but arrived well-labeled by Barrow, frequently with dates and captions for each image.
The collection also includes materials from Wilhelmina Barrow, Lionel's mother, relating to her service in the American Red Cross during World War II and in the post-war period. Wilhelmina's materials include ARC training and recruitment documents, her transport papers, newspapers and other publications geared toward servicemen and women, reports from Red Cross Clubs, suggested itineraries for traveling Europe while on leave, and souvenirs from her trips to Italy, France, and Belgium. Also included in this section are reports and clippings about the National Council of Negro Women; Barrow was a member for some time during the 1950s and 1960s. Some of these materials relate to segregation and discrimination.
Acquired as part of the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture.
Clippings (information artifacts); African Americans in mass media; Minorities in journalism; Journalism -- Education; Minorities and journalism; World War, 1939-1945 -- War work -- Red Cross; Washington (D.C.); World War, 1939-1945 -- Women -- African Americans; Photographs; American Red Cross; United States. Army. Infantry Regiment, 24th -- History; National Council of Negro Women; National Association of Black Journalists; John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture; Howard University. School of Communications; Barrow, Lionel C., 1926-2009; Barrow, Lionel C., 1926-2009; Association for Journalism and Mass Communication; Association for Journalism and Mass Communication. Minorities and Communication Division
- Subject Files, 1
  - African Americans in broadcasting/films, 1 boxes (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes Barrow's subject and clippings files on Black broadcasting, as well as files for various films with African American protagonists.
  - Freedom's Journal research, 1 boxes (Box 2)
    Includes research, photocopies, and notes by Barrow created in preparation for his unpublished book on Freedom's Journal. Topics include 19th century African American education, the slave trade, literacy, and legal policy.
  - Freedom's Journal research, 1 boxes (Box 3)
    Includes research, photocopies, and notes by Barrow created in preparation for his unpublished book on Freedom's Journal. Topics include minorities in journalism, chapter drafts, and various notes about the newspaper.
  - Name Files, 1 boxes (Box 4)
    Barrow's clippings and name files for African American historical figures, celebrities, journalists, and activists.
  - Assorted Subject Files, 1 boxes (Box 5)
    Contains Barrow's subject files on various topics relating to African American history and culture, such as Black women (including actresses and other celebrities), Black artists/filmmakers, and other topics relating to African American popular culture.
  - Freedom's Journal research, 1 boxes (Box 6)
    Includes research, photocopies, and notes by Barrow created in preparation for his unpublished book on Freedom's Journal. Box contains chapter drafts/notes, analysis, and miscellaneous files related to research for the project.
  - Brown vs. Board of Education Supreme Court decision, 0.5 boxes (Box 10)
    Barrow's clippings and research files created in the 1990s as he wrote an article analyzing media coverage of the Brown vs. Board of Education desegregation case in 1954. Includes files about various newspapers in Atlanta.
  - Statistical Research Files, 0.5 boxes (Box 10)
    Barrow's subject files on statistical research concepts and best practices.
  - Journalism/Journalist ethics files, 1 boxes (Box 7)
    Barrow's clippings and subject files about the journalism profession, particularly journalism ethics and minorities in journalism.
  - Assorted Subject Files, 1 boxes (Box 8)
    Contains Barrow's unsorted subject and clippings files on a wide range of topics, including education, women's rights, racism, Washington DC history, healthcare and addiction issues, and advertising. Includes a file with several issues of Race Relations Reporter (1973-1974).
  - Assorted Subject Files, 0.75 boxes (Box 13)
    Contains Barrow's unsorted subject and clippings files on topics such as minority employment, minorities in media/communications, population statistics, African American community businesses, and economics. Includes incomplete issues of The Star newspaper (1949-1950).
  - Advertising Subject Files, 1 boxes (Box 9)
    Barrow's clippings and subject files about media and advertising, particularly for minority communities. Includes files about the power of Black consumers, racism in advertising, and other topics related to African Americans in media.
  - Assorted Subject Files, 1 boxes (Box 30)
    Barrow's clippings and subject files on assorted topics, including Freedom's Journal agents and supporters and views of the presidents on race. Also includes articles and writings by Barrow.
  - Assorted Subject Files, 1 boxes (Box 31)
    Barrow's clippings and subject files on various topics, including views of the presidents on race and his historical research. There are also writings by Barrow.
  - Assorted Subject Files, 1 boxes (Box 32)
    Barrow's clippings and subject files, including those on historical research; African Americans in the press; and Martin Luther King, Jr.
  - M. L. King subject file, 2 boxes (Box 33, 34)
    Barrow's subject file on Martin Luther King, Jr., and his death.
- Academia/Advertising Work, 2
  - Teaching/Courses, 1980s-1990s; 1 boxes (Box 11)
    Assorted files related to courses, subjects, and lectures prepared by Barrow, largely from the 1980s and 1990s, relating to his role as Howard University professor and dean. Includes files on courses and other topics in broadcasting, advertising, minorities in journalism, statistics, mass media, racism in language, and other issues.
  - Teaching/Courses, 1980s-1990s; 0.5 boxes (Box 12)
    Assorted files related to courses, subjects, and lectures prepared by Barrow, largely from the 1980s and 1990s, relating to his role as Howard University professor and dean. Includes files on courses and other topics in broadcasting, advertising, minorities in media, racism, and the media's impact on the African American community.
  - Barrow's college/graduate studies, 1940s-1960s; 0.5 boxes (Box 12)
    Student work and course files from Barrow's education at Morehouse College and the University of Wisconsin. Includes some files from the preparation of his dissertation.
  - Foote, Cone, and Belding Advertising: Report: Is there a Black Market? Are Special Market Efforts Needed to Reach It?, 1976; 1 folders (Box 13)
  - Foote, Cone, and Belding Advertising reports and speeches, 1966-1967; 1 folders (Box 13)
    Prepared by Barrow while he served as Associate Research Director.
  - Foote, Cone, and Belding recruiting, 1968-1971; 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Foote, Cone, and Belding appraisal of minority recruitment program, 1969; 1 folders (Box 13)
  - Burrell Ad Agency and Foote, Cone, and Belding, 1982; 1 folders (Box 13)
  - Barrow Information Group materials, 1987-1990s; 0.5 boxes (Box 17)
    Client/potential client files: largely consists of Barrow's files tracking his cold contacts for various universities and colleges, seeking work for the Barrow Information Group research consultancy that he founded; also includes some articles and freelance work, including a book review by Barrow for The Black Press.
- Professional Organizations, 3
  - Allied Lodge No. 1170, 1984 (Box 12)
  - American Association of Advertising Agencies, 1969-2004 (Box 12)
  - American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education, 1989 and undated (Box 12)
  - American Association for Public Opinion Research, 1974 (Box 12)
  - American Overseas Association, 1954 (Box 12)
  - American Sociological Society, 1950-1955 (Box 12)
  - Association of Black Colleges and J and MC Programs, undated (Box 12)
  - America's Black Forum, 1978 (Box 12)
  - Athlete Career Connection (Arthur Ashe), 1991 (Box 12)
  - Accrediting Council on Education in JMC (Box 12)
  - American Council on Education, 2004 (Box 12)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Summer Program, 1970s (Box 12)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Convention, 1997-2000 (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): TWELVE CSM News letter, 1992-2005 (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Communication T, 2002-2005 (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): The Founding of Division, 1970-1971 (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Alumni, 1972-1987 (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Paper on minority division, 1980-1985 (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Journalism Leadership Institute for Diversity (JLID), 1988-1989, 1999-2001; 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Affirmative action, 2000-2001 (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Minority women article correspondence, 2000s (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Speech, 1992 (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Dreyfuss Affair commentary, 1976 (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): FCC, 2001 (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Resolution, 2001; 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): conference analysis, 1967-1990 (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Miscellaneous papers and clippings, 1975-2001 (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Reorganization, 1978-1979 (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Ad Hoc Committee on Minority Education, 1968-1971 (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Minorities into the mainstream, 1985 (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Minorities and communication division's conference plans, 1977 (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Contacts to make, 1998-2001 (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Task Force on Diversity, 2005 (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Convention in Ottawa, 1975 (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Correspondence, 1968-1970 (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Minorities in Media, 1974-1975 (Box 14)
    Annual reports, newsletter, and misc
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): AEJMC standing committee reports, 2000-2001 (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Newsletters, 1974-2002; 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Becker diversity study, 2001 (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): History division, 1999-2002 (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Public relation division, 1990, 2001 (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Liason, 1998-2001 (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Endowment committee, 1965-1971 (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Advertising Division, 1968-2000 (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Communication Theory and Methodology Division (CT, 1969-1995, 2000-2001; 4 folders (Box 14)
    Annual reports, scholarship correspondence, donations, travel grants
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Diversity studies and reports, 1969-1990 (Box 14)
  - Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC): Meetings, conventions, and conferences, 1969-1982; 4 folders (Box 14)
    Annual reports, correspondence, convention reports
  - Minorities and Communication Division (MAC): Heads, 1970-2002 (Box 14)
  - Minorities and Communication Division (MAC): Correspondence, reports, evaluations, 1970-2002; 4 folders (Box 15)
  - Minorities and Communication Division (MAC): Newsletter, 1971-2006; 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Minorities and Communication Division (MAC): Beginning, 2007 (Box 15)
  - Minorities and Communication Division (MAC): Accomplishments, 1968-2000 (Box 15)
  - Minorities and Communication Division (MAC): Membership, 1971-1989, 2001; 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Minorities and Communication Division (MAC): Annual reports, 1971-2001; 4 folders (Box 15)
    Annual reports and mid-year reports
  - Minorities and Communication Division (MAC): Diversity studies and reports, 1969-2002 (Box 15)
  - Minorities and Communication Division (MAC): Things to do, undated (Box 15)
  - American Indian Graduate Center, 2004 (Box 15)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity, Inc. (APA), 1998-1999 (Box 15)
  - Asian and Pacific Islander American Scholarship Fund (APIASF), 2004 (Box 15)
  - Advertising Research Foundation, 1983 (Box 15)
  - Association for the Study of African American Life and History (ASALH): Tampa Bay Chapter, 2007-2008; 5 folders (Box 15)
    Historical memories, speeches, convention plans
  - Association of Schools of Journalism and Mass Communication (ASJMC), 2004 (Box 15)
  - ASPIRA, Inc.: The fifth annual youth leadership convocation, 2004 (Box 15)
  - Afro-Urban Institution, Inc., 1970s (Box 15)
  - Association for Women in Communications, 2004 (Box 15)
  - Black Business Council, 1987 (Box 15)
  - California Chicano News Media Association (CCNMA), 2004 (Box 15)
  - Capital Press Club conference re: Black Communicators, 1970 (Box 15)
  - Chela Education Financing, 2004 (Box 15)
  - Crazy Hourse Memorial Foundation, 2004 (Box 15)
    Awards
  - Corportation for National Community Service, 2004 (Box 15)
    Scholarships
  - Council for Opportunity in Education (COE): TRIO, 1999-2008; 9 folders (Box 15)
  - Council for Opportunity in Education (COE): TRIO, 1999-2008; 5 folders (Box 16)
    Magazines, memorandum, booklets, website information
  - Consortium for a Strong Minority Presence, 2004 (Box 16)
  - Obama Election: Democratic Party Envolvement, 2007-2008; 9 folders (Box 16)
    Clippings, Compaign materials, donation, committee plans
  - Dow Jones Newspaper Fund, 2002-2004 (Box 16)
  - FCC Material, 1979-1980 (Box 16)
  - Freedom Forum, 2004-2005 (Box 16)
  - Gates Millennium Scholars, 2004 (Box 16)
  - Hispanic College Fund, Inc., 2004 (Box 16)
  - Hispanic Scholarship Fund, 2004 (Box 16)
  - Kaiser Family Foundation, 2004 (Box 16)
  - Knight Foundation, 2002-2004 (Box 16)
  - LAGRANT Foundation, 2004 (Box 16)
  - Lumina Foundation for Education, 2002-2004 (Box 16)
  - LIN Television: Scholarship, 2004 (Box 16)
  - Motion Picture Association of America, Inc., 1957-1993 (Box 16)
  - Minority Media Means Money (4M) Conference, 1971; 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Newspaper Association of America, 2003-2004; 2 folders (Box 16)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP): Act-50, 1994 (Box 16)
  - NBA Broadcast Scholarship, 2003 (Box 16)
  - National Association of Black Journalists (NABJ), 1987-1992, 2004, 2005-2007; 3 folders (Box 16)
  - National Association of Hispanic Journalists (NAHJ), 2004 (Box 16)
  - National Black Media Coalition, 1982 (Box 16)
  - Native American Journalists Association (NAJA), 2004 (Box 16)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH), 2004 (Box 16)
  - National Newspaper Publishers Association, 2004 (Box 16)
  - National Press Club: NPC Scholarship, 2004 (Box 16)
  - National Science Foundation (NSF), 2003-2004 (Box 16)
  - Organization of Chinese Americans (OCA), 2004 (Box 16)
  - Poynter Institute, 2004 (Box 16)
  - PRB Summit, 1971 (Box 16)
  - Public Relations Society of America, 2004 (Box 16)
  - University of the Virgin Islands, 2004 (Box 16)
  - Radio-Television News Directors Association Foundation (RTNDA), 2004 (Box 16)
  - University of Southern California: Financial Aid, 2004 (Box 16)
  - Scripps Howard Foundation, 2004 (Box 16)
  - St. Louis Post-Dispatch Meeting, 1975-1976 (Box 16)
  - Sallie Mae Fund, 2004 (Box 16)
  - Southern Newspaper Publishers Association Foundation (SNPA), 2004 (Box 16)
  - Society of Professional Journalists (SPJ), 2004 (Box 16)
  - Minorities in the Newspaper Business, 1987-1990 (Box 16)
  - Unity Democrat (newspaper), 1962 (Box 16)
  - Wilmington 10 Defense Committee, 1976 (Box 16)
- Personal Files, 4
  - Calendars, 1994-2000 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous personal correspondence, 1970s-1990s; 3 folders (Box 18)
  - Stamp collecting materials, undated (Box 18)
  - Awards and certificates, 1944-1997 (Box 18)
    Includes 2 plaques.
  - Morehouse College papers, clippings, 1947-1949; 2 folders (Box 18)
  - U.S. National Student Association, 1949 (Box 18)
  - "Famous Folks" photograph albums, undated; 4 albums (Box 18)
  - "Les Girls" photograph albums, undated; 4 albums (Box 18)
  - Correspondence, press releases etc., re: Barrow's Army enlistment/reporting for service/service in Korea: 1950 July/Aug.-1951, 1950 July-1951; 5 folders (Box 19)
  - Photographs and captions from Barrow's service in the Korean War, 1950-1951 (Box 19)
  - Barrow's correspondence to Wilhelmina Barrow from Korea, 1950-1951 (Box 19)
    Includes annotated copy of Congressional Record, 1951 Oct. 10.